<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content"><channel><title>lsvra</title><description>When in doubt, delete it.</description><link>https://lsvra.com</link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 23:25:28 +0100</lastBuildDate><pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2020 23:25:28 +0100</pubDate><ttl>250</ttl><atom:link href="https://lsvra.com/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://lsvra.com/posts/pihole-vodafone-router</guid><title>Pi-hole &amp; Vodafone Router: Make them work together</title><description>A guide on how to setup your Pi-hole alongside Vodafone's Smart Router 2.0 (Huawei HG8247Q) and still keep your TV service functioning.</description><link>https://lsvra.com/posts/pihole-vodafone-router</link><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 18:00:00 +0100</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<h1>Pi-hole &amp; Vodafone Router: Make them work together</h1><p>I'm always thinking about on how can I help the people around me to have more online privacy.</p><p>This can be challenging sometimes. People tend to have a lot of devices, and I don't want to constantly bother them with tech related tips &amp; tricks.</p><p>Recently, I've managed to take some time to figure out a way of adding a thin layer of security to my home network. So everyone who uses it, benefits from it.</p><p>The trick was to go directly to the source. <strong>The router</strong>.</p><h2>Meet Pi-hole</h2><p>Pi-hole acts as a DNS sink hole, intercepting the DNS requests before they leave your network and blocking the bad ones from actually being made.</p><p>Since it works at the DNS level, every device inside your home will be protected by it.</p><p>You can learn more about the project on <a href="https://pi-hole.net">their website</a>. For now, I invite you to try this with me. 👨‍💻</p><h2>Requirements</h2><p>In this tutorial I'll be using:</p><ul><li>A Raspberry Pi 3B+ (but you can use any model)</li><li>An ethernet cable (to make the connection between the Raspberry Pi and the router)</li><li>A 32GB MicroSD card</li><li>The MacOS Terminal app</li></ul><blockquote><p>If you use Windows, try <a href="https://www.putty.org">Putty</a> for the ssh connection and <a href="https://www.balena.io/etcher/">balenaEtcher</a> for the OS flashing part.</p></blockquote><h2>Setting up your Raspberry Pi</h2><p>Download and extract the latest Raspberry Pi OS Lite image from the <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads/raspberry-pi-os/">official website</a>. Be sure you pick the <strong>Lite</strong> version. We won't need GUI for our Pi-hole build.</p><p>Insert an empty MicroSD card into your computer.</p><p>Open a terminal window inside the same folder of the Raspberry Pi OS image and run the following command:</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">diskutil list
</code></pre><p>This will give you the disks that are currently mounted on your computer.</p><p>Example (the MicroSD card is /dev/disk2 - your disk and partition list may vary):</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">❯ diskutil list
/dev/disk0 (internal):
    #:                       TYPE NAME                    SIZE       IDENTIFIER
    0:                       GUID_partition_scheme        500.3 GB   disk0
    1:                       EFI EFI                      314.6 MB   disk0s1
    2:                       Apple_APFS Container disk1   500.0 GB   disk0s2

/dev/disk1 (synthesized):
    #:                       TYPE NAME                    SIZE       IDENTIFIER
    0:                       APFS Container Scheme -      +500.0 GB   disk1
                             Physical Store disk0s2
    1:                       APFS Volume Macintosh HD     89.6 GB    disk1s1
    2:                       APFS Volume Preboot          47.3 MB    disk1s2
    3:                       APFS Volume Recovery         510.4 MB   disk1s3
    4:                       APFS Volume VM               3.6 GB     disk1s4

/dev/disk2 (external, physical):
    #:                       TYPE NAME                    SIZE       IDENTIFIER
    0:                       FDisk_partition_scheme       *15.9 GB    disk2
    1:                       Windows_FAT_32 boot          268.4 MB   disk2s1
    2:                       Linux                        15.7 GB    disk2s2
</code></pre><p>Unmount the MicroSD card, replacing <strong>N</strong> with the correct number.</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">diskutil unmountDisk /dev/diskN
</code></pre><p>Then flash Raspberry Pi OS into it. Again, replace <strong>N</strong> with the disk number like you did before.</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">sudo dd bs=1m if=path_of_your_image.img of=/dev/rdiskN; sync
</code></pre><p>This can take a few minutes. Check the progress by pressing <strong>Ctrl + T</strong>.</p><p>After the <strong>dd</strong> command finishes, eject the MicroSD card (replacing <strong>N</strong> one more time).</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">sudo diskutil eject /dev/rdiskN
</code></pre><p>In order to have remote access to the Raspberry Pi after the installation, you'll need to setup <strong>ssh</strong> next.</p><p>The process is super easy. You will create an empty file named <strong><em>ssh</em></strong> at the root folder. The Raspberry Pi OS will check that file on boot and enable <strong>ssh</strong> for for us.</p><p>So, mount the MicroSD card again by removing and insert it back into the computer.</p><p>Then check the available volumes:</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">ls /Volumes
</code></pre><p>You will see your MicroSD card name (eg: <strong>boot</strong>). Use it to create the <strong>ssh</strong> file.</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">echo "" &gt; /Volumes/{your_card_name}/ssh
</code></pre><p>Congratulations! You now have a fully working Raspberry Pi OS build! 🎉</p><p>Please eject your MicroSD card and head over to the next segment.</p><h2>Setting up Pi-Hole</h2><p>Insert your MicroSD card into the Raspberry Pi.</p><p>Connect the Raspberry Pi to the router using an ethernet cable.</p><p>Turn on the Raspberry Pi.</p><p>Open a web browser window and type:</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">192.168.1.1
</code></pre><p>Then press <strong>enter</strong>. Your router's access page should be presented.</p><p>Look at the back of your router and use those credentials to log in.</p><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-1.png" alt="Router access page"/><p>Once you got in, click on <strong>Wired Devices</strong>. You'll see the IP address attributed to the Raspberry Pi. This will be your <strong>ssh</strong> door from now on.</p><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-2.png" alt="Router main page"/><p>You'll now access the Raspberry Pi through <strong>ssh</strong>. Open a terminal window and (using the Raspberry Pi IP address) run:</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">ssh pi@192.168.1.79
</code></pre><p>It will ask you for the <strong>ssh password</strong>. The default one is <strong>raspberry</strong>.</p><p>The first thing you'll need to do after the login, is to change the default password. Run:</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">raspi-config
</code></pre><p>This allows you, among other things, to change the default password for the Raspberry Pi. Feel free to explore the other options.</p><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-3.png" alt="Raspi-config screen"/><p>Once the basic configuration is done, update and reboot the system.</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get upgrade
sudo reboot
</code></pre><p>Log in into your Raspberry Pi again (using the new password) and run Pi-hole's <strong>one step automated install</strong> command.</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">curl -sSL https://install.pi-hole.net | bash
</code></pre><p>To move around during the install phase use the <strong>tab</strong> and <strong>arrow keys</strong>. Press <strong>space</strong> to select the options and <strong>enter</strong> to proceed to the next step.</p><h4>Select the Upstream DNS Provider (eg: Cloudflare)</h4><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-4.png" alt="Upstream DNS Provider screen"/><h4>Select the default Blocking Lists (default: All)</h4><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-5.png" alt="Blocklists screen"/><h4>Select the network protocols (default: IPv4 &amp; IPv6)</h4><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-6.png" alt="Network Procols screen"/><h4>Confirm the IP adresses for the Raspberry Pi and Gateway (router)</h4><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-7.png" alt="IP confirmation screen"/><h4>Install the web interface (default: ON)</h4><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-8.png" alt="Web interface screen"/><h4>Install the web server (default: ON)</h4><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-9.png" alt="Web server screen"/><h4>Activate query logging (default: ON)</h4><p>PS: I recommend turning this <strong>OFF</strong>. Explanations in the next step.</p><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-10.png" alt="Query logging screen"/><h4>Choose your Privacy Mode (default: Show Everything)</h4><p>PS: I recommend your choose the Anonymous Mode (3) to protect the privacy of everyone. Doing so, you will not be able to see which domains are the users acessing. But also, <strong>why should you?</strong> 🤔</p><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-11.png" alt="Privacy Mode screen"/><p>Last but not least, <strong>save the admin webpage login password</strong>. This will be your key to the Pi-hole's web interface.</p><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-12.png" alt=""/><p>Alright! You have successfully installed Pi-hole on your Raspberry Pi. Let's put it to work! 🚀</p><h2>Configuring Pi-Hole</h2><p>Using your current <strong>ssh</strong> terminal session, lets edit <strong>dhcpcd.conf</strong> file by running:</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">sudo nano /etc/dhcpcd.conf
</code></pre><p>Change the file's last few lines in order to look like this (the static ip address should be the same as your Raspberry Pi + the /24 suffix):</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">interface eth0
    static ip_address=192.168.1.79/24
    static routers=192.168.1.1
    static domain_name_servers=127.0.0.1
</code></pre><p>Save it by pressing <strong>Ctrl + X</strong> and accepting the changes.</p><p>Once again, reboot the Raspberry Pi.</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">sudo reboot
</code></pre><blockquote><p>The next steps will halt your internet/tv connection for a few minutes. If you find yourself stuck, just undo the changes.</p></blockquote><p>Open your <a href="http://192.168.1.1">router access page</a> again and <strong>disable</strong> the DHCP and DHCPv6 servers. You'll be using Pi-hole from now on.</p><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-13.png" alt="Router DHCP screen"/><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-14.png" alt="Router DHCPv6 screen"/><p>Open Pi-hole's web interface in your web browser (using your Raspberry Pi IP address).</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">192.168.1.79/admin
</code></pre><p>Log in using the admin password you got at the end of the Pi-hole instalation.</p><p>Turn on the DCHP server by enabling the following boxes and set the range between <strong><em>192.168.1.64</em></strong> and <strong><em>192.168.1.251</em></strong>. Don't forget to press the <strong>Save</strong> button.</p><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-15.png" alt="Pi-hole DCHP settings screen"/><p>Enable the IPv6 Upstream DNS Servers as well.</p><img src="https://lsvra.com/images/posts/pihole-vodafone-router/pihole-vodafone-router-16.png" alt="Pi-hole Upstream DNS settings screen"/><p>Your network should now be working again. But not your TV connection.</p><h2>Re-enabling the TV connection</h2><blockquote><p>Without this step you won't be able to watch TV since the IPTV service needs to access Vodafone's own DNS servers.</p></blockquote><p>You'll need to write down the MAC address of the TV Box. You can find it in the <strong>bottom of the device</strong> itself or under <strong>Wired Devices</strong> by accessing your router access page.</p><p>The MAC address should be something like this:</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight"> aa:bb:cc:dd:ee:ff
</code></pre><p>In your <strong>ssh</strong> terminal window, run the following command:</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">sudo nano /etc/dnsmasq.d/03-vodafone.conf
</code></pre><p>Now, add the following text to the created file (change the MAC address by the one you wrote down):</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">dhcp-host=aa:bb:cc:dd:ee:ff,set:vodafone
dhcp-option=tag:vodafone,option:dns-server,192.168.1.1
</code></pre><p>Save the file by pressing <strong>Ctrl + X</strong> and accepting the changes.</p><p>You can check if the file was successfully created by running:</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">ls /etc/dnsmasq.d
</code></pre><p>Finally, reboot the system.</p><pre><code class="language-no-highlight">sudo reboot
</code></pre><p>Reboot your TV Box.</p><p>You just created a bypass for the TV service to work under the same rules as defined by Vodafone.</p><h2>Final Tips</h2><p>Feel free to tweak the remaining Pi-hole settings as you wish.</p><p>I recommend you to add more blocklists to the Pihole, specially <strong>one specific for your home country</strong>. Just do a web search, there are great sources available.</p><blockquote><p>Note that, Pi-hole uses a specific type of list. You cannot use the same lists that common adblockers do.</p></blockquote>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>